A Register of the Lawrence Samuels collection
Hoover Institution Archives
Lawrence Samuels collection
1942-1988
2007C18
Samuels, Lawrence
15 manuscript boxes 6.25 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Materials relating to Libertarianism and Libertarian organizations collected by Lawrence Samuels, who is the Vice Chair of the Libertarian Party of Monterey County, and Northern Vice Chair of the Libertarian Party in California.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives for further information.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2007
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography / Administrative History
Lawrence K. Samuels is editor and a contributing author of Facets of Liberty: A Libertarian Primer. He serves as the Northern California vice chair of the Libertarian Party. He also co-chairs Monterey County Libertarians for Peace.
Lawrence K. Samuels won honorable mention at the East of Eden Writers Conference in 2002 for his historical novel Ferret: The Reluctant King. He is a member of the California Writers Club and was the editor of Rampart Institute's quarterly magazine in the early 1980s.
Samuels is a graduate of California State University at Fullerton (1976), where he minored in journalism. He was the editor-in-chief and a columnist for the campus newspaper at Fullerton College. He later wrote guest columns for the Orange County Register, the third largest newspaper in California. He managed the Future of Freedom Conference series for five years in Southern California, arranging speaking engagements for Timothy Leary, Ray Bradbury, Arthur Laffer, Karl Hess, Nathaniel Brandon, and dozens of other scholars and writers.
Scope and Content of Collection
Materials relating to Libertarianism and Libertarian organizations collected by Lawrence Samuels, who is the Vice Chair of the Libertarian Party of Monterey County, and Northern Vice Chair of the Libertarian Party in California.
The Libertarian Party materials are comprised of printed materials documenting the activities the Libertarian Party in general and California Libertarian Party in particular. Documents include information about the bylaws, platform, principals, and issues of the Libertarian Party. Collected materials focus on election materials, Libertarian Party conventions, conferences, background materials and writings, correspondence, and a list of Free Enterprise Organizations around the world.
Libertarian (and non Libertarian) publications include books and periodicals, pamphlets, newsletters, bulletins, journals, and magazines and newspapers. Although libertarianism is usually considered a conservative ideology, other conservatives often argue that government is needed to maintain social order and morality. They argue that excessive personal freedoms encourage dangerous and irresponsible behavior. Some of the most commonly debated issues are sexual norms, the drug war and public education. Most of the publications are for those interested in individual liberty and the philosophy behind politics.
Books series includes libertarian books published by Lawrence Samuels and Robert Le Fevre – a Libertarian businessman, radio personality and primary theorist of autarchism (a political philosophy that upholds the principle of individual liberty, rejects compulsory government, and supports the elimination of government in favor of ruling yourself and no other).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series: Libertarian Party materials, Libertarian publications, Publications (non Libertarian), and Books.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in Stanford University's online catalog.
Subjects
Libertarian Party; Libertarianism – United States; Libertarianism – California; Presidents—United States—Election; Elections – California; Education - California; California – Politics and government; Students for a Libertarian Society; Student movements – United States; Laissez-faire; Bergland, David
Container List
- Libertarian Party materials, 1950-1985. (Box 1)
  Legal documents, correspondence, statements, advertisements, announcements, promotions, flyers, speeches, reports, and writings, arranged into groups by subject
  - General
    - Bylaws of the Libertarian party, adopted in convention, New York City, 1983 September 1-4 (Folder 1: 1)
    - Platform of the party (Folder 1: 2)
      - General
      - 1972
      - 1974
      - 1976
      - 1980
    - Statement of principals, undated (Folder 1: 3)
    - Libertarian party on the issues (Folder 1: 4)
      - Agriculture
      - Controlled substances
      - Election laws
      - Gay rights
      - Government and business
      - Health care
      - Poverty
      - Women's rights
    - Correspondence, 1952-1983 (Folder 1: 5)
    - Advertisements, announcements, promotions, 1977-1984 (Folder 1: 6)
    - Flyers, bumper stickers, 1971-1984 (Folder 1: 7)
    - List of Free Enterprise Organizations (confidential), typescript. (Folder 1: 8)
      Includes report on INFRA's activities, 1964-1965
  - Election materials
    - General, 1979 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Presidential candidates
      - John Hospers, 1972 (Folder 1: 10)
      - Roger MacBride, 1976 (Folder 1: 11)
      - Ed Clark, 1980 (Folder 1: 12)
      - David Bergland, 1984 (Folder 1: 13)
    - United States Senate (Folder 1: 14)
      - Stormy Mon, undated
      - Lynn Kinsky, 1976
      - William White, 1984
    - United States Congress (Folder 1: 15)
      - Jeff Mandel, 1982
      - Dana Rohrabacher, 1989 (?)
    - Governor/Lieutenant governor, Libertarian party (Folder 1: 16)
      - Gary Greenberg, New York, 1978
      - John Vernon, California, 1982 (?)
      - Dan Dougherty, California, 1982
    - Mayor (Folder 1: 17)
      - Fran Youngstein, New York City, 1973
      - Ray Cunningham, San Francisco, 1979
    - Miscellany, undated (Folder 1: 18)
  - Libertarian Party Conventions
    - London convention of the Libertarian International, the second world libertarian convention, 1984 (Folder 1: 19)
    - National (Folder 1: 20)
      - 1977
      - 1985
    - Libertarian party of California (Folder 1: 21)
      - 1976
      - 1977
      - 1978
      - 1981
  - Future of Freedom conference series (Folder 1: 22)
    - General, 1980s
    - 1981
    - 1982
    - 1983
    - 1984
    - 1985
    - Survey of opinion
  - State Libertarian party materials (Box 2)
    - California, 1971-1983
      - General, 1972-1981. (Folder 2: 1)
        Includes platform of the Libertarian party of California, 1974-1976
      - San Francisco Bay area, 1973 (Folder 2: 2)
      - Orange County, 1971-1983 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Georgia, 1983-1984 (Folder 2: 4)
    - New Jersey, 1979
    - Texas, 1986
  - Collected materials
    - Association of Libertarian Feminists, 1974-1981 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Campus Studies Institute, San Diego, California, 1971-1972 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Foundation for Economic Education, Irvington-on-Hudson, New York, 1950-1970. (Folder 2: 7-8)
      Includes correspondence, pamphlets, notes, and reports
    - Institute for Human Studies, Menlo Park, California, 1961-1973. (Folder 2: 9-10)
      Includes annual reports, correspondence, meeting notices, and other material
    - New Right Coalition (individuals for rational society), 1971-1974 (Box-folder 3: 1)
    - Society for Individual Freedom, undated. (Folder 3: 2)
      Includes correspondence dated 1953
    - Society for Individual Liberty, 1970-1974 (Folder 3: 3)
    - Society for Libertarian Life, 1977-1982 (Folder 3: 4)
    - Young Americans for Freedom, 1969-1974 (Folder 3: 5-6)
    - Young Americans for Freedom, 1969-1974 (Box-folder 4: 1)
  - Collected writings
    - Bastiat, Frèdèric, The State, 1955 (Folder 4: 2)
    - Bergland, David, Libertarian candidate for President of the United States, Libertarianism in One Lesson, 1984
    - Bergland, David, The Politics of Freedom, America's Libertarian heritage, undated
    - Bird, Mary Carol, Capsule Course In Community Press Relations, written for Young Americans for Freedom, Washington, D.C.
    - Bonjarski, Stefan, The Gods and Their Defenders, Pacific Libertarian, 1973
    - Botsford, David, Industry and State: Myth and Reality, undated
    - Breggin, R. Peter, The Psychiatric Holocaust, undated
    - Callaway, Howard, Up Against the Yaf Wall, 1969 July
    - Casterline, C. James, The Agora, 1971
    - Childs, R. A., Jr., An Open letter to AYN Rand: Objectivism and the State, 1969
    - Clifton, Merritt, Freedom, undated
    - Cobb, Joe, The Income Tax Must Go!, 1982
    - Collier, Peter, The Next American Revolution: The Libertarian party Wants to Set You Free, 1979
    - Cooper, Richard, review on Joe David's book The Fire Within Alexandria, undated
    - Curley, Charles, Critical Essay, undated
    - Curley, Charles, The Future of the Libertarian Movement, presented to the Society for Libertarian Life, 1982 September 26
    - Delain, Gail, Secret Project Ho-Hum, undated
    - Dematteis, Philip, What is Libertarianism?, 1976
    - Ebeling, Richard, In Defense of Free Migration, Libertarian Reprints, an occasional publication of the Libertarian Alliance, London, England, 1979
    - Ely-Chaitlin, Eric, The last Crusade, 1985
    - Grey, John, The System of Ruins, 1983
    - Hartwell, R. M., History and Ideology, 1974
    - Hoar, William, Watching Libertarians In Convention, 1975 September
    - Hospers, John, second annual Fourth of July Address, Paternalism in America, undated
    - Hummel, Jeffrey Rogers, The Case for Legalizing Heroin, undated
    - Jenkins, John, Free Thinkers, 1980
    - Konkin, Samuel Edward, An Agorist Primer, 1986
    - Kuklinsky, T., Political Definitions, undated
    - Kuklinsky, T., Economics, undated
    - LeFevre, Robert, The Strategy of Apathy, undated
    - MacBride, Roger, The Libertarian Challenge: A New Direction for America, 1975
    - MacCallum, Spencer, Drafting a Constitution for Orbis: The Business of Providing Community Services in Space, undated
    - Meinshausen, Donald, Rohrabacher as Renegade Radical Reagan Republican, undated
    - Micklethwai, Brian, Freedom Order and Architecture, 1983
    - Mints, Frank, Debacle in Vietnam, 1969
    - Mises, Ludwig, von, Middle-of-the Road Policy Leads to Socialism, an address, 1965 (?)
    - Moore, Thomas, The New Libertarians Make Waves, 1985
    - Moreell, Ben, an address, It is not Enough to be an Engineer, 1964
    - Nolan, David, Classifying and Analyzing Politico-Economic System, 1971
    - Pugsley, John, Viewpoint of the Month, 1978-1984
    - Raimondo, Justin, Tear Down the walls!, 1979
    - Rand, Ayn, The Shanghai Gesture, 1972
    - Richman, Shel, The Great Auto-Import Rip-off, 1981
    - Rothbard, Murray, From the desk of Murray N. Rothbard, undated
    - Saunders, Richard, The M Strategy, undated
    - Smith, George, transcript of a speech, The Corruption of Freedom in Classical Liberalism, 1977 February 20
    - Shenfield, Arthur, An Heir to Adam Smith, 1974
    - Tame, Chris, Ernest Hemingway and the Failure of Nihilism, 1980/1981
    - Wheler, Richard, The Fascist Threat to America, undated
    - Wright, Nelson, Uncle Sam's Phony Express, 1974
    - Yench, John, articles from Christian Laissez Faire, 1973-1974
- Libertarian publications, 1961-1988.
  Books and periodicals, pamphlets, newsletters, bulletins, journals, and magazines and newspapers, arranged by physical form
  - Books and periodicals
    - Alternative Bookshop, specialists in libertarian books in all subjects, London, England, undated (Box 4)
    - Book News, published by Academic Associates Incorporated, Los Angeles, California, 1969; 1972-1973
    - Campus Organizing Manual, published by Young Libertarian Alliance, Washington, D.C., undated
    - Eden Press, privacy catalog, protection business plans opportunities options, Fountain Valley, California, undated
    - Free Market Yellow Pages, directory of truly free-market businesses and organizations, sponsored by Rampart Institute and Agora Association of Businesses, 1983-1985
      (Lawrence Samuels project)
    - Humanist Century, published by the Humanistic Science Inc., 1983; 1985 (Folder 4: 5)
    - Institute for Rational Emotive Therapy, New York, 1983/1984
    - Liberty Book Store, Libertarianism: A Recommended Reading List, undated
    - Index on Liberty: An International Directory of Institutions and Publications of Interest to Promoters of Reason and Liberty, a supplement to Free World Chronicle, Bergen, Norway, 1984
    - Books for Libertarian
      - Catalog, winter, Washington, DC, 1973-1974
      - Bulletins, Washington, DC, 1972-1974
    - Laissez Faire Books, the world's largest selection of book on Liberty, New York
      - Laissez Faire Books (catalog), New York
        - undated (Folder 4: 6)
        - 1984-1988 (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - Anarchist Catalog, 1980; 1983 (Folder 5: 2)
      - Catalog and Review, 1973-1981
      - Libertarian catalog, New York, 1974 May
      - Review, 1973-1975
    - L.M.P – Libertarian microfiche publishing, literature list, 1983 (Folder 5: 3)
    - Libertarian Connection, published by Natalee Hall and Skye D'Aureous, 1969-1972 (Folder 5: 4)
    - Libertarian Review, Washington, DC, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 6: 1)
    - Liberty, Mountain View, California, spring 1977
    - Publications of the Institute of Economic Affairs, London, England. Distributed in North America by Transatlantic Arts, Inc., Levittown, New York, 1977
    - Rampart Institute (non-profit, tax-deductible, educational organization), Student and General Educational Catalog, Carmel, California, 1984
    - Society for Individual Liberty Speakers Bureau, booklet, Silver Spring, Maryland, 1971
    - University Bookman, quarterly review, New York, 1968-1969 (Folder 6: 2)
  - Newsletters
    - A is A, writings on freedom and individualism, Brighton, Michigan, 1972-1973 (Folder 6: 3)
    - Abolitionist, publication of the Radical Libertarian Alliance, 1971
    - Activist Letter, Students for Libertarian Society, Warminster, Pennsylvania, 1983
    - American Anarchist Tradition, Westfield, New Jersey, undated
    - American Defense, Libertarian Defense Caucus, Colton, California, 1982-1984
    - Anchorage Libertarian Newsletter, published by the Libertarian Party of Anchorage, Alaska, 1986
    - California Libertarian News, Libertarian Party of California, 1987
    - Caltech Liberty, Caltech Libertarian Alliance, 1979
    - Campus Report, published by the Intercollegiate Society of Individualists, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1962-1966
    - Center for Libertarian Studies Newsletter, New York, 1977 (Folder 6: 4)
    - Channel Counties Libertarian, Santa Barbara and Ventura counties, Southern California), 1983
    - Chronicle, Libertarian International, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 1981-1982
    - Common Sense, Libertarian Party of Florida, Miami, Florida, 1980-1985
    - Dialogue on Liberty, Young Americans for Freedom, 1977-1979
    - East Bay Libertarian Lifeline, Oakland, California, 1981
    - East Bay LP News, Berkeley, California, 1976
    - Free Marin, San Rafael, California, 1986
    - Free New Mexico, Libertarian Party of New Mexico, Sapello, New Mexico, 1987
    - Free Texas Reports, Libertarian party of Taxes, Houston, 1983
    - Free World, Digest of the Libertarian International, Toronto, Ontario, Canada, 1982
    - Freedom Network News, published by Libertarian
    - Frontlines, Santa Barbara, California, 1980; 1982
    - Georgia Libertarian, Libertarian party of Georgia, 1984
    - Hawaii Libertarian, Honolulu, 1978
    - Headlines, Fountainhead Club Libertarians for Gay Rights, Los Angeles, California, 1984
    - Individualist, published by the Intercollegiate Society of Individualists, Inc., 1957-1964 (Folder 6: 5)
    - Individual Liberty, Society for Individual Liberty, Warminster, Pennsylvania, 1977; 1984-1987 (Folder 6: 6)
    - Innovator, applications, experiments, and advanced developments of liberty, Los Angeles, California, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 7: 1-2)
    - LibSIG (international libertarian special interest group in Mensa), San Francisco, California, 1980-1981 (Folder 7: 3)
    - LFL Reports, Libertarian for Life, Wheaton, Maryland, 1981; 1986
    - Libertarian, California Libertarian Party, Burlingame, California, 1972
    - Libertarian, George Washington University, Washington, D.C., 1962
    - Libertarian, Wenonah, New Jersey, 1967
    - Libertarian Alternative, Travis County Libertarian Party, Taxes, 1973
    - Libertarian Alternative Newsletter, San Diego, California, 1980-1982
    - Libertarian American, Center for Libertarian Studies, San Antonio, Taxes, 1967-1970
    - Libertarian Digest, Berkeley, California, 1985
    - Libertarian Chronicle, San Diego Libertarians, California, 1982
    - Libertarian Church Newsletter, First Libertarian Church Newsletter, Los Angeles, California, 1977-1986 (Folder 7: 4)
    - Libertarian Forum, New York, 1975-1983 (Folder 7: 5-6)
    - Libertarian Review, Libertarian Review Inc., Washington, D.C., 1974-1975 (Box-folder 8: 1)
    - Libertarian Transition Caucus Newsletter, Los Angeles, California, undated
    - Libertarian Party on Campaign Issues, Libertarian Party, Washington, D.C., 1982
    - Libertarian Super Club of Los Angeles, 1972-1973
    - Libertarian Vision, Libertarian Party of Florida, Orlando, 1986
    - Libertarie, Libertarian Party of Quebec, 1977
    - Libertas Review, Society for Libertarian Life Associated Students, Inc. California State University Fullerton, 1980-1984
    - Limit! Libertarian Republican Alliance, New York, 1975-1978
    - Market for Liberty, Libertarian party of Oregon, 1976; 1978
    - Michigan Libertarian, Libertarian Party of Michigan, 1986
    - Movement for Independent Pacific Channel Islands, Avalon, California, 1983
    - New Capitalist Digest, Pasadena, California, 1971
    - New Libertarian Strategy of the Movement of the Libertarian Left, New Libertarian Enterprises, Long Beach, California, 1980
    - New Libertarian Weekly (First Newsweekly of the New Libertarian Society), 1976-1978 (Folder 8: 2)
    - New Libertarian Weekly Supplement, New Libertarian Enterprises, Long Beach, California, 1984
    - Newsletter, Progress party of New South Wales, registered by Australia Post Publication, Sylvania, Australia, 1985-1986
    - Newsletter of the Libertarian Supper Club of Orange County, California, 1981
    - Now and After, Libertarian Socialist Newsletter, 1977
    - Orange County Libertarian, Huntington Beach, California, 1978
    - Oregon Libertarian, McMinnville, Oregon, 1985
    - Palmetto Libertarian Forum, forum for members of the South Carolina Libertarian Party, Columbia, South Carolina, 1985
    - Peterborough Libertarian Association, Peterborough, Ontario, Canada, 1980-1981 (Folder 8: 3)
    - Porcupine, serving Idaho, Wyoming and Montana, Missoula, Montana, 1980-1981
    - Prometheus, Libertarian Futurist Society, Rochester, New York, 1984-1985
    - Pursuit of Liberty, Center for Libertarian Studies, New York, 1977-1981
    - Rampart College Newsletter, Santa Ana, California, 1972
    - Sandhills Libertarian Gazette, Libertarians in the South Carolina Midlands, West Columbia, South Carolina, 1985-1987
    - San Diego Libertarian, San Diego Libertarian Party, San Diego, California, 1985-1986 (Folder 8: 4)
    - Society for Individual Liberty News, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1970-1973 (Folder 8: 5)
    - Southern Libertarian Messenger, Florence, South Carolina, 1986 (Folder 8: 6)
    - Tactics of the Movement of the Libertarian Left, Long Beach, California, 1983-1984
    - Tanstaafl! Published by the Rational Libertarian Church, Fort Collins, Colorado, 1973
    - Taxes Libertarian, LPT Activists, San Antonio, Texas, 1985; 1987
    - Thorn, Ann Arbor Anarchist Coalition, a part of the Michigan region of the Radical Libertarian Alliance, undated
    - Torch, Grove City College Conservative Club, Grove City, Pennsylvania, 1969
    - Torch, Galatians Fellowship of California, 1980
    - United Libertarian Fellowship, Yorba Linda, California, 1978-1979
    - Virginia Libertarian, Richmond, Virginia, 1985
    - Washington Libertarian, Libertarian Party of Washington State, Tacoma, Washington, 1983
    - Westside Libertarian, Libertarian party of California, Los Angeles, 1987
  - Bulletins (Box 9)
    - Against the Wall, Westfield, New Jersey, volume one, number 10, undated (Folder 9: 1)
    - Bay Area Libertarian, San Francisco Bay Area Libertarian Party, San Francisco, California, 1977
    - Bulletin – Newsletter of the Ontario Libertarian Party, Toronto, Ontario, 1985-1986
    - California Activist, Libertarian Party of California, San Jose, California, 1983-1984
    - Dissent, TDT-Libertarian Enterprises, Cupertino, California, 1986-1978
    - Free Life, journal of the Libertarian Alliance, London, England, 1981-1983
    - Free Marin, journal of ideas for the liberation/free market community, Kentfield, California, 1987 (Folder 9: 2)
    - Illinois Libertarian, Chicago, Illinois, 1981
    - Indian Libertarian, incorporating the Free Economic Review and The Indian Rationalist, an independent journal of Economic and Public Affairs, Bombay, 1961
    - Invictus, journal of individualist thought, Hollywood, California, 1970; 1973
    - Libertarian Alliance, (Independent non-party group), Libertarian Alliance Ltd., London, England, undated
    - Libertarian Bulletin, Libertarian Party of Australia, Campbelltown, South Australia, 1982-1985
    - Libertarian Iconoclast, Alliance of Libertarian Activists, Berkeley, California, 1968-1969
    - Libertarian News, occasional review of British, European and World Libertarian news, issued by the Libertarian Alliance, London, England, 1984
    - Libertarian Vanguard, Libertarian party Radical Caucus, Palo Alto, California, 1982
    - LP News, National Office of the Libertarian Party. Aurora, Colorado, 1974
    - Preform-Inform, Libertarian Press Association, information exchange among Libertarian Nomads, 1969 (Folder 9: 3)
    - Principle, Libertarian party of Canada, Ontario, Canada, 1977; 1980
    - Southern Libertarian Messenger, Florence, South Carolina, 1985-1986
    - Update: ?n the Libertarian Movement, Libertarian Review Foundation, Washington, D.C., 1982
    - Volition, libertarian review, Redlands, California, 1969
  - Magazines
    - Against the Wall, Self-Liberation and Voluntary Alternatives, Westfield, New Jersey, 1980 (Folder 9: 4)
    - Cambridge Liberator, Cambridge, England, issue one, undated
    - Efficacy, Gulf Coast Voice of Civil and Economic Liberty, Houston, Taxes, 1979
    - Elf, journal for left-tight libertarian expression, 1980
    - Freedom's Child, literary journal, published by Anglican Enterprises, Grover City, California, 1982 (Folder 9: 5)
    - Free World Chronicle, Libertarian International World Headquarters, volume III, number 5, 1986
    - Integrity, member of the Libertarian Press Association, 1971
    - Liberator: An Academic Voice for Individualism, 1961-1962, New Orleans, Louisiana
    - Libertarian Connection, member of the Libertarian Press Association, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 10: 1-2)